<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: etc | TaberBlog]]></title>
  <link href="http://ataber.github.com/blog/categories/etc/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ataber.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-30T15:23:42-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://ataber.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrew Taber]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Give Up]]></title>
    <link href="http://ataber.github.com/blog/2013/06/30/just-give-up/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-30T15:10:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ataber.github.com/blog/2013/06/30/just-give-up</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The other day I decided to walk away from a weightlifting session after having only done two sets. I hadn't made progress in days and every session I seemed to get weaker. So I quit. Only temporarily, but I needed it badly.</p>


<br />


<p>After days of not making substantial progress on an endeavor that is central to my ego-health, I have a tendency to lean in to the frustration. My capacity for focus and my determination curdle in the white-hot frustration and my effort turns into an engine producing nothing of value, only more frustration.</p>


<br />


<p>So I've tried a new tactic: diversify my ego investments to prevent this from happening, and if it still happens, remember that the body and mind work best when loaded with a sinusoidal pressure, and prepare for that slump of downtime we all need once in a while.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Treat Job Prospects Like Humans]]></title>
    <link href="http://ataber.github.com/blog/2013/04/25/treat-job-prospects-like-humans/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-25T17:06:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ataber.github.com/blog/2013/04/25/treat-job-prospects-like-humans</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've been applying to a lot of jobs lately, and I've noticed that a
surprising number of shops, even startups, do not treat me like a human. One
place (a small startup with no HR department) even sent me an email a month and
a half after I'd applied with instructions about how to sign up for some service
they use to screen job applicants. Not even a "thank you for applying", not even
a personalized email. Not even on time (I've accepted another offer already) and
not even with a reference to the original company I was applying to (only by
googling the person who sent the email did I find out what company they were
from).</p>


<p>And you complain about not being able to find talent?</p>


<p>I call bullshit.</p>


<p>I answered a job post on HackerNews and I got a canned response that was
faulty in every way. And you expect me to believe you're going to treat your
customers, investors, and employees any better?</p>


<p>Or how about another company which posts jobs to HackerNews just about every
week with a puzzle in it that is completely incomprehensible and must be solved
<strong>TO EVEN EMAIL THEM</strong>? Obviously all your employees are automatons, because
presumably you're treating me like you treat them.</p>


<p>The digital age has been dramatically labor-reducing in a lot of ways. But
so many people don't leverage the technology we have today <strong>to make
interactions more, rather than less, personal</strong>. AirBnB does this, why can't
everyone?</p>


<p></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Autonomy of the Avatar]]></title>
    <link href="http://ataber.github.com/blog/2013/02/17/autonomy-of-the-avatar/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-17T16:25:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://ataber.github.com/blog/2013/02/17/autonomy-of-the-avatar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's often said that anonymity is the distinguishing, delightful, and dangerous property of the internet. 
Anonymity is blamed as the factor causing internet trolls and low-quality
discourse online, but I believe the more harmful phenonenon the internet creates
opportunity for is something I call autonomous avatars. 
<br>
<p>With Facebook, Twitter or Reddit, it becomes possible within minutes to forge a 
new personality. In fact, not only is it possible, but practically omnipresent: how
many people do you know who selectively post to Facebook in order to create a more
aesthetically pleasing version of themselves?
<br>
<p>These avatars we create for ourselves are becoming a source of motivation: 
pictures are taken for the sole purpose of posting to Facebook, for example.
These avatars in a sense become autonomous. The identities we craft online 
affect how we behave in a bizarre feedback loop.
<br>
<p>But this doesn't qualify as dangerous yet. What I believe makes the autonomous
avatar more dangerous than anonymity is the fact that in a truly anonymous situation,
repercussions of actions are nonexistent. This precludes positive social reinforcement as
much as punishment. Without social reinforcement, the group is less likely to become
a torch-carrying mob. However, when we introduce artificial identities, it is more likely
that cognitive dissonance motivates behavior that would otherwise be unthinkable.
<br>
<p>I believe this is why bullying on Facebook is much more dangerous than that on 4chan.
The bullys on Facebook have a facade to hold up, and this pushes antisocial behavior to a whole other level.

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
